Guide to the Frances P. Taft Papers, 1942-2008
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Frances P. Taft Papers
1942-2008
Taft, Frances P.
2.75 cubic feet (9 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence, subject files, news clippings and manuscripts documenting Frances P. Taft’s tenure with the Alumnae and Aulmni Association of Vassar College (AAVC),as well as documentation of her coursework (Class of 1942) at Vassar College.
Biographical Note
Frances Taft (1921-2017), VC ‘42, was President of Vassar College’s Alumnae Association (AAVC) from 1965-1971. Taft graduated from Vassar with a major in biology and a minor in art history, and went on to establish a career in art education, teaching at the Cleveland Institute of Art (1950 - 2012) after earning a master’s degree in art history from Yale in 1948. She served as President of Alumnae and Aulmni Association of Vassar College (AAVC) when the College initiated debate over shifting to co-education. Taft was the first recipient of the AAVC Award for Outstanding Service to Vassar College in 2001. She received the award once more in 2011, along with other former presidents of the alumnae/i association.
Frances Taft’s commitment to Vassar College extends to her time as an undergraduate student, when she served as president of the Vassar College Athletic Association. After graduating in 1942, Taft joined the first officer class of the U.S. Naval Reserve's Women Accepted for Volunteer Emergency Service (WAVES). She and her husband Seth Taft, grandson of President William Howard Taft, moved to Cleveland where she joined the faculty at the Cleveland Institute of Art and served as chair of the department of art history and liberal arts. She served as a Vassar College Trustee, president of the AAVC Board of Directors, as well as various committees and Vassar clubs.
Scope and Content Note
The Frances P. Taft Papers include extensive correspondence between Taft and Alumni Association members, association administration, including college presidents and faculty. Subject files document Taft’s responsibilities within the Alumni Association, highlighting chapters in Vassar’s history focusing on the college’s shift to co-education, debate regarding its merger with Yale University, shifts in curriculum to expand science and technology coursework, issues involving Black student movements and general political strife in the country during the late 1960s. Papers include handwritten drafts of Taft’s Alumni Association talks presented both on campus and during tours throughout the country, status reports documenting association fundraising efforts including management and upkeep of the college’s Alumnae House building.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Garnsey, Gertrude, 1904-1989; Simpson, Alan, 1964-1977
Organizations:
Alumnae and Alumni of Vassar College (Organization); Vassar College. Alumnae House; Vassar College. Kendrick House; Vassar College. Walker Field House; Vassar College--Buildings; Vassar College--Alumni and alumnae; Yale University
Subjects:
Coeducation; Students, Black--United States
VCL Categories
Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Mark Seidl, February 2021. Updated January 2022.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Frances P. Taft, February 2013.
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1966-2002; (Box 1-3, 9)
  This series is organized into two subseries and arranged chronologically within each subseries. The first includes letters from Frances Taft to and from members of the alumni association and college administration, including Gertrude Garnsey, Faith Scott, and Vassar College President Alan Simpson. The second subseries includes letters to Taft from colleagues and associates, and often contain carbon copies of Taft’s own letters. Correspondence to Alumni Association members are arranged by subject as well as correspondent name, as filed by the creator. Taft’s correspondence documents alumnae/i involvement in Vassar College’s debate over co-education, potential merger with Yale University, and management of student unrest during the late 1960s.
- Series II. Subject Files, 1942-2008; (Box 3-9)
  This series is organized into two subseries and arranged alphabetically, as filed by the creator, within each subseries. Content covers Taft’s extensive involvement with discussions addressing Vassar’s shift to co-education (late 1960s), student unrest on campus during the late 1960s, Black student movements on campus (late 1960s, early 1970s), including housing, shifts in curriculum to science and technology coursework (1970s), and general management and fundraising efforts of the Alumni Association, including the management and upkeep of Vassar’s Alumnae House (1987 - 1993). Files also include documentation of class reunion event logistics, surveys sent to alumnae, and symposia created for Vassar College alumnae/i, including topics such as Classroom 1968: Our Environmental Predicament, Classroom 1969: The Question of Privacy, Classroom 1971: Perspectives on Population, Classroom 1974: The Time Crisis.
- Series III. Clippings, 1967-2006; (Box 8)
  The newspaper clippings in this series, collected and arranged by the creator, document the potential proposed merger of Vassar College and Yale University (late 1960s).
- Series IV. Writings, 1966-2006; (Box 8-9)
  Manuscripts in this series include speeches and talks given by Frances Taft at various alumnae/i events, Vassar Club gatherings, retirements, memorials and symposia.
- Series V. Coursework, 1938-1942; (Box 3, 12, 13)
  Files contain class notes, finaly papers, syllabi, and coursework illustrations.
- Series VI. Scrapbooks, 1938-1945; (Box 10-11)
  2 scrapbooks containing Vassar memorabilia, ephemera, and clipings.
- Series VII. Sound Recordings, 1940; (Box 10)
  Vassar Glee Club, 1865-1940 record set.
- Series VIII. Potographic Prints, 1925-2007; Box 19
  Photographs of Prindle family, Vassar College reunions, and Class of 1942.
Container List
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Correspondence from Frances Taft to AAVC
    - General, 1967-1970 (Folder 1.1)
    - AAVC members, 1969 (Folder 1.2)
    - Board of Trustees, 1969-1976 (Folder 1.3-1.5)
    - Club correspondence, 1970-1972 (Folder 1.6-1.7)
    - AAVC President, 1968-1987 (Folder 1.8-1.9, 9.1)
    - AAVC Vassar/Yale, undated (Folder 1.10)
    - Alumnae House fundraising, 1996-2002 (Folder 1.11)
    - Garnsey, Gertrude, 1965-1969 (Folder 2.1-2.4)
    - Scott, Faith, 1969-1972 (Folder 2.5-2.7)
    - Simpson, Alan, 1968 (Folder 2.8)
  - Correspondence to Frances Taft
    - General, 1980-1992 (Folder 2.9-2.11)
    - AAVC, Board of Trustees, 1968-1969 (Folder 3.1)
    - AAVC members, co-ed debate, 1969 (Folder 3.2)
    - Class of 1942, 25th reunion, 1966-1980 (Folder 3.3-3.4)
    - Class of 1942, council representation, 1973-1995 (Folder 3.5)
    - Gert Garnsey Fund, search committee, 1968-1971 (Folder 3.6-3.8)
- SERIES II. SUBJECT FILES
  - AAVC
    - Alumnae House, fundraising committee, 1999 (Folder 3.9)
    - Alumnae House, liquor license, 1967 (Folder 3.10)
    - Alumnae House, task force, 1986 (Folder 14.12)
    - Annual Fund, resolution of Board of Trustees, 1968-1974 (Folder 3.11)
    - Annual Meetings, 1966-1972 (Folder 3.12-3.13)
    - Athletics, Walker House, 1978-1979 (Folder 3.14)
    - Black Students, sit-in, master plan, Vocational Bureau, 1969 (Folder 3.15)
    - Black Studies, housing, 1969-1974 (Folder 9.2)
    - Board materials, 1959-1969 (Folder 4.1)
    - Board minutes, 1966-1968 (Folder 4.2)
    - Board of Trustees materials, 1975-1978 (Folder 14.5-14.6)
    - Board reports, 19780-1981 (Folder 14.3-14.4)
    - Board, announcements, correspondence, 1967-1968 (Folder 4.3)
    - By-law, revisions, 1969-1978 (Folder 9.3)
    - Candidates for Vassar College President, 1976-1977 (Folder 4.4)
    - Centennial celebration, speeches, 1971 (Folder 14.7-14.8)
    - Class 1942 reunuions, 1966-1967 (Folder 14.9-14.11, 19.3)
    - Class 1942 reunions, 1990-2008 (Folder 4.6-4.8, 15.2, 16.9,)
    - Class of 1963 reunion, 2005 (Folder 15.3,)
    - Class reunion logistics, 19979 (Folder 14.12, 15.1,)
    - Class reunion song lyrics, [undated] (Folder 14.13,)
    - Cleveland Vassar Club, 1971-2007 (Folder 15.4-15.5, 16.10,)
    - Co-education, special meeting, notes, remarks, 1969 (Folder 4.5)
    - Committee on New Dimensions, George Langdon, 1967 (Folder 4.9)
    - Council Meeting notes, correspondence, 1967-1968 (Folder 4.10)
    - Cross, Nancy, 1979-1980 (Folder 15.6,)
    - Faculty Tenure Reports, 1974-1975 (Folder 4.11)
    - Garnsey, Gertrude, interview, 1978 (Folder 4.13, 15.9)
    - Garnsey, Gertrude, Vassar memories, undated (Folder 4.12)
    - The Individual in Mass Society, Pres. Simpson's remarks, 1977-1978 (Folder 4.14)
    - Joint Development efforts, AAVC and Vassar College, 1974-1976 (Folder 15.7-15.8, 17.11)
    - Kendrick House, Black student housing, 1972-1974 (Folder 5.1)
    - Letter to Alumni, President's Report, 1971-1972 (Folder 5.5)
    - Long Range Planning Committee, 1996-1997 (Folder 5.6)
    - Meeting notes, newsletters, 1966-1972 (Folder 5.2)
    - Memoranda, 1978 (Folder 14.1)
    - Memoranda, notes, letters, 1989-1997 (Folder 5.7)
    - Nominating committee, 1969-1970 (Folder 5.3)
    - President Simpson, statements, violence and vandalism, 1967-1980 (Folder 5.4)
    - Regional Meeting, Cleveland, OH, 1973 (Folder 5.8)
    - Report on the Program of Case Testing and Feasibility Dtermination, 1979 (Folder 15.10)
    - Reunions, 1972 (Folder 5.9)
    - Search Committee, Executive Secretary, 1972-1974 (Folder 5.10)
    - Self Evaluation, Review of Alumni Structures, 1975-1976 (Folder 5.11)
    - Seminar, Seven Colleges Meeting, Alumni Associations, 1966-1968 (Folder 5.13, 1511)
    - Seminar, The Sea-Citizens Perspective on a Changing Frontier, 1979 (Folder 5.12)
    - Symposium, Alumni Week, AAVC Centennial, correspondence, speech transcripts, 1971 (Folder 5.14-5.15)
    - Taft bio, awards, 2009 (Folder 6.1)
    - Taft speaking tour, notes, memoranda, agendas, 1969-1970 (Folder 6.2)
    - The Individual in Mass Society, Pres, Simpson's remarks, 1977-1978 (Folder 4.14)
    - Thompson, C. Mildred, dedication, 1970 (Folder 6.3)
    - Vassar Club Workshop, 1970 (Folder 6.4)
    - Vassar Institute of Technology, Women's Studies, Alumni questionnaire, 1970-1972 (Folder 6.5)
    - Vassar Quarterly, financial review, 1974-1977 (Folder 6.6)
    - Workshop, Cleveland, OH, 1973 (Folder 6.7)
    - Women's Studies, Yale/Vassar, 1971-1972 (Folder 6.8)
    - Yale merger, trustee statements, 1967 (Folder 6.9)
    - Year end update, capital campaign for Vassar College, 1993-1995 (Folder 6.10)
  - General
    - Ad hoc Committee on Capital Priorities, 1979, 1982 (Folder 16.1)
    - Alumnae House, background, history, 1942-1971 (Folder 6.11)
    - Alumnae House, closure, alum response, 1987-1993 (Folder 6.12-6.13)
    - Alumnae House, joint committee, 1994-1995 (Folder 6.16-6.17)
    - Alumnae House, long range planning, program expansion, 1995-1996 (Folder 7.1)
    - Alumnae House, research trip to Wellesley, 1995-1996 (Folder 7.2)
    - Alumnae House, research, notes, budgets, 1992-1996 (Folder 6.14-6.15)
    - Blanding, Sarah Gibson, 1967 (Folder 16.2)
    - Board of Trustee materials, 1968-1975 (Folder 16.3)
    - Board of Trustee reports, 2000-2002 (Folder 16.4)
    - Board of Trustees, Lotos Club, 1988-1979 (Folder 16.5)
    - Buildings and Grounds, Art Department, 1979-1980 (Folder 16.6)
    - Capital Campaign, 1969-1972 (Folder 16.7)
    - Centennial, International Conference, 1960-19761 (Folder 16.8)
    - Clark, Evelyn, resignation, 1970 (Folder 7.3)
    - Classroom 1963-Ecology coursework, 1962-1963 (Folder 7.4)
    - Classroom 1963-The City (Folder 9.4)
    - Classroom 1965-Moral Values in a Changing Society (Folder 7.5)
    - Classroom 1967 (Folder 7.6)
    - Classroom 1968-Our Environmental Predicament (Folder 7.7)
    - Classroom 1969-The Question of Privacy (Folder 7.8)
    - Classroom 1971-Perspectives on Population (Folder 7.9)
    - Classroom 1974-The Time Crisis (Folder 7.10)
    - Co-Education, Board of Trustees reports, 1975-1978 (Folder 7.12)
    - Co-Education, reports, 1974 (Folder 7.11)
    - Energy Efficiency proposal, 1982 (Folder 16.11)
    - Faculty, Johnson, Glen, 1976 (Folder 7.13)
    - Faculty, McConnell, Emma, 1973-1974 (Folder 7.14)
    - Farm study, 1975 (Folder 16.12)
    - Friends of Vassar Art Gallery, 1975-1977 (Folder 16.13)
    - Friends of Vassar Art Library, 1986 (Folder 16.14)
    - Friends of Vassar Loeb Art Center, 19780-2004 (Folder 16.15, 17.1-17.9)
    - Fundraising and Public Relations, 1976 (Folder 17.10)
    - Garnsey, Gertrude, retirement gift, 1985 (Folder 7.15)
    - Graduate Center, establishment, 1970-1971 (Folder 7.17)
    - Graduate Center, review for Vassar College, 1969 (Folder 7.16)
    - Healey, Bernardine, 1986 (Folder 17.12)
    - Hemlock, Christine, 1969-1974 (Folder 7.18)
    - Mudd Chemistry Building, dedication, 1979-1984 (Folder 7.19)
    - Oh My God It's Monday, song lyrics, Class of 1942, undated (Folder 9.5)
    - Parietal regulation debates, 1969 (Folder 9.6)
    - Student Sit-In, faculty firings, 1971 (Folder 8.1)
    - Physical Education, athletics, 1978-1983 (Folder 17.13)
    - Promotional materials, Vassar College, 1966-1977 (Folder 18.1)
    - Pyramid Society, 2004-2007 (Folder 18.2)
    - Seven Colleges, conference, 1970 (Folder 8.3)
    - Smith, Virginia, 1980-1985 (Folder 18.5)
    - Speeches, articles by Taft, Simpson, Havelock, Purcell, 1950s, 1973-1977 (Folder 18.3, 19.4)
    - Springside Estate, 1969 (Folder 18.4)
    - Student Sit-In, faculty firings, 1971 (Folder 18.1)
    - Student unrest, 1969-1970 (Folder 8.2)
    - Students for a Democratic Society, student unrest, 1969 (Folder 8.4)
    - Trustee bios, 1972-1979 (Folder 18.6)
    - Vassar buildings and grounds, chapel addition, 1984-1985 (Folder 8.5)
    - Vassar Club history, photocopies, 1890s-1920s (Folder 18.7)
    - Vassar College budget Committee, tuition, compensation, 1980-1983 (Folder 8.6)
    - Vassar Farm, 1975-1978 (Folder 8.7)
    - Vassar Today, event guest list, 1982 (Folder 18.8)
    - Vassar writings, by students, 1985 (Folder 18.9)
    - Walker Field House, building reports, 1979-1981 (Folder 8.8)
- SERIES III. CLIPPINGS
  - John Paul Miller, article by Frances Taft, Metalsmith Magazine, 2006, fall (Folder 8.9)
  - Vassar/Yale, 1967 (Folder 8.10)
- SERIES IV. WRITINGS
  - AAVC Centennial, 1971 (Folder 8.11)
  - Article, John Paul Miller, Cleveland Institute of Art, 1985, 2005 (Folder 8.12)
  - Gertrude Garnsey article, undated (Folder 8.13)
  - Lecture, Wasmer Gallery, Cincinnati, 1987-1990 (Folder 8.14)
  - Speech, AAVC Award Acceptance, 2001 (Folder 8.15)
  - Speech, AAVC talks, Taft as President, 1966-1972 (Folder 8.16)
  - Speech, Eulogy for Mimi Obler, 1995 (Folder 8.17)
  - Speech, Laurel School Commencement, 2006, 2010 (Folder 8.18)
  - Talks, articles, misc., 1968-2006 (Folder 8.19)
  - Vassar Club talks, Hartford CT, Cleveland OH, 1971-1974 (Folder 9.7)
  - Vassar Quarterly, articles, 1973 (Folder 8.21)
  - William Howard Taft, 2002 (Folder 8.20)
- SERIES V. COURSEWORK
  - Biology, 1940 (Folder 12.1)
  - Biology Lab, 1936-1940 (Folder 12.2-12.4)
  - Chemistry, 1939 (Folder 12.5-12.6)
  - Economics 105, 1940 (Folder 12.7-12.10)
  - English 105, 1940 (Folder 12.12)
  - English 218, 1940 (Folder 12.13)
  - English IV, 1938 (Folder 12.11)
  - Histology, 1942 (Folder 13.1)
  - Introduction to Philosophy, 1939 (Folder 13.2)
  - Photography class, scrapbook, 1940 (Folder 13.3)
  - Tissue Culture, biology, 1940 (Folder 13.4)
  - Zoology 105, 1940 (Folder 13.5)
  - Zoology 105, lab, 1941 (Folder 13.6-13.9)
  - Zoology 260b, 1941 (Folder 13.10)
  - Zoology 380, 1939 (Folder 13.11)
  - Zoology 380a, 1942 (Folder 13.12)
  - Zoology 500, 1941 (Folder 13.13)
- SERIES VI. SCRAPBOOKS
  - Vassar College Scrapbook, 1938-1940 (Folder 11.1)
  - Vassar College Scrapbook, 1941-1945 (Folder 10.1)
- SERIES VII. SOUND RECORDINGS
  - Vassar Glee Club, Vassar Choir, 1865-1940 (Folder 10.2)
- SERIES VIII. PHOTOGRAPHIC PRINTS
  - Prindle family, 1925-1927 (Folder 19.1)
  - Vassar College Class of 1942, reunions, 1970s-2007 (Folder 19.2)